<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-03-08T16:14:58-06:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ERIN WILLS</title><subtitle>By possessing both technical and managerial skills,  Erin is highly adaptive particularly with learning and teaching new technology.
</subtitle><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">The Art of Communicating…</title><link href="/articles/interests/2023-03-07-generation_communication/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art of Communicating…" /><published>2023-03-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T15:55:47-06:00</updated><id>/articles/interests/generation_communication</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/interests/2023-03-07-generation_communication/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was about two years ago when I started getting many arbitrary questions from people about my personal interests.  Most of these questions did not really fit into the conversation and seemed to be thrown in on a whim.  It made me very curious about what the person was thinking right before they asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to be reflective afterwards and evaluate whether something I was doing had dictated the shift in conversation.  Maybe I was the cause of this behavior:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was I being too candid so they wanted to change the subject?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was I talking too little so they wanted to change to a more general topic?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was I talking too much about something they didn’t care about?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Had I said something and this was this a test to find out more information about me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could not come up with anything that would be obvious.  In general, we were just having a casual conversation.  At the time I just shrugged off the moment as a random event but I noticed a trend starting to build over time. It didn’t really matter where the conversation took place - work, gym, coffee shop, restaurant, elevator, etc.  It didn’t really matter what brought us together - neighbor, co-worker, date, random person, etc.  If the person was under 40 years old then I typically had a similar reaction with maybe the occurances being more frequent with younger people.  Each person was interested in my personal interests and this was fine until I tried answering their questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have interests but I realized that I communicate those interests differently.  I talk about my interests by describing it and what I gain from it.  For example, I take bicycle rides frequently becasue I like the exercise, being outside, and exploring new places - I feel more invigorated afterwards.  In contrast, the person I was talking to described the physical description - brand, special features, color - and how they came into ownership of it.  As much as I appreciated the origin story of her bicycle, I really wondered if she actually likes riding and what motivates her to ride.  My follow up question of why do you like riding resulted in a vague ‘it is something I just like’ type of answer.   I realized that the people I was talking to were conveying very concrete and non-personal information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if I was the early teen version of myself with the social skills often confused with a person on the high functioning portion of the autism spectrum then I might really enjoy these conversations.  We could take turns sharing facts.  These facts would lead to first person recounts of a past experience.  Maybe there would be a moment where they would have had a similar experience and it would be their time to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I am not that person anymore so this encounter is not exactly fulfilling or even interesting to me anymore.  Some stories like this are important and sometimes you need something like this to fill time but ultimately there should be a bit more to a conversation.  What is interesting from this experience is how often I experience or overhear people having these rote conversations.  When I try to create a deeper conversation then you would not believe the shock the person has.  It’s like in the back of their mind is a voice saying ‘those are secrets that only I can know’ or maybe for the skeptic the voice says ‘that information tells them too much about me’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe these reactions are just due to the people being young.  Many people in their 20s and 30s have always had technology like a cell phone and in recent years have been more isolated due to covid.  I’m at the older end of that age spectrum and was a teenager or young adult during the beginning of the tech boom.  I will definitely attest that my generation used technology in destructive ways.  Just look at television, music, and apps that came out between 2000-2010 and you will notice a signficant amount of salacious content and promotion of stereotypes.  It was difficult to get away from these influences and I think people mimicked this ‘environment’ in their own lives.  Living through that time period meant that you learned to assess people’s intentions and really decide what you wanted out of the interaction.  Thinking back on those times, I think younger generations might think we were fairly crazy but learned to be unfazed by people and seek out honest responses that matched our standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to live in this dual culture, where older Millennials experienced the wild west of a social and technology paradigm shift and younger people experiencing only the after effects of the shift, the two groups will need to learn how to negotiate their differences of communication and risk taking.  I know that I will need to change how I talk in personal settings because the person might not be as open with their true opinions and feelings and that I might be too abrupt.  It will be interesting to see how the generations differ as time progresses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="interests" /><category term="Interests" /><category term="entertainment" /><summary type="html">So it was about two years ago when I started getting many arbitrary questions from people about my personal interests. Most of these questions did not really fit into the conversation and seemed to be thrown in on a whim. It made me very curious about what the person was thinking right before they asked.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/phones.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/phones.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Random Blog..</title><link href="/articles/interests/2023-03-07-interests_blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Random Blog.." /><published>2023-03-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T15:56:40-06:00</updated><id>/articles/interests/interests_blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/interests/2023-03-07-interests_blog/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I developed this Jekyll website, I realized that I wanted to add short essays for several purposes, but for mainly two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To let people know my professional opinions and exeriences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To let people know my technical knowledge and long-term goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website was originally designed for a single blog section but I wanted to segment my content into a file structure so if I wanted to rebrand or change the purpose of the website then all the content in a folder could be easily removed or hidden.  In the end, I had two sections as outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This worked initially until I realized that people were often interested in knowing my personal intersts and wanted to foster more of a connection with me as a person.  So this led me to create a third section where I can put random thoughts, entertainment and short stories about my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section entitled “The Random Blog” is aimed as a location where I can put those posts while keeping the other two blog’s purposes distinct.  In the near future I will also add tags so it is easier to find related posts with a simple click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy and please keep in mind that the writings in this section are not meant to be taken to heart but are intended as interesting conversation starters that will hopefully lead to a meaningful debate or reflection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="interests" /><category term="Interests" /><category term="professionalism" /><summary type="html">As I developed this Jekyll website, I realized that I wanted to add short essays for several purposes, but for mainly two reasons:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/library.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/library.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Git…</title><link href="/articles/tech/2023-02-22-git/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Git…" /><published>2023-02-22T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:05:53-06:00</updated><id>/articles/tech/git</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/tech/2023-02-22-git/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say that I have really enjoyed learning git.  Every project I do, I learn to appreciate it a bit more.  Part of my interest is for a completely oddball reason - I like using terminal since it fits well in my workflow.  I can have a prototype of an idea created that shows basic functionality of the initial goals. This is my proof of concept.  After I am at that stage then I can start having fun with it and start looking at these changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;modifying the code to meet a style guide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;refactoring the code to improve it’s modular nature and organization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;evaluating code efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;brainstorming how the code may affect future feature additions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving existing features&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating new features&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identifying time consuming processes and automating&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adding graphics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a user interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a private and public portal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adding utilities and operation analysis tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;planning pipelines processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating transition plans to move processes from one cloud service to another&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;brainstorming modularity and code ownership among teams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;evaluating change processes and personnel risks (onboarding/offboarding)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these items could be explored by making a branch.  In many cases I might have an idea and just need a fast testing platform that I could keep if it works or throw away.  Here are some uses of git besides creating a branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow multiple people to develop code for one branch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow branches of branches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow tested and verifed code to merge into a primary branch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;update a branch’s code with an updated base branch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;revert changes to a previous commit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;checkout a concurrently developed code branch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;search for code changes from weeks, months, or years ago that may could to be repurposed or a cause of a current problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;track project progress through purpose created branches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;store code in a cloud based system that has all past change logs included&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;through cloud services, manage code through automated approval and setup processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Add info about naming conventions
– GitKracken
– Sourcetree&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="tech" /><category term="Tech" /><category term="tools" /><summary type="html">I have to say that I have really enjoyed learning git. Every project I do, I learn to appreciate it a bit more. Part of my interest is for a completely oddball reason - I like using terminal since it fits well in my workflow. I can have a prototype of an idea created that shows basic functionality of the initial goals. This is my proof of concept. After I am at that stage then I can start having fun with it and start looking at these changes:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/moon_phases.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/moon_phases.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stategic Thinking…</title><link href="/articles/tech/2023-02-20-strategic_thinking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stategic Thinking…" /><published>2023-02-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:10:10-06:00</updated><id>/articles/tech/strategic_thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/tech/2023-02-20-strategic_thinking/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple travel assessment like Gravity diagram&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alarm development of single and elapsed time alarms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="tech" /><category term="Tech" /><category term="eda" /><category term="overview" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/train.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/train.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Regression…</title><link href="/articles/tech/2023-02-17-regression/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regression…" /><published>2023-02-17T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:05:34-06:00</updated><id>/articles/tech/regression</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/tech/2023-02-17-regression/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regression is not a topic that I originally spent much time thinking about but as I started to get more involved with analyzing large dataset, I found myself learning more about regression so I coud extract the most out of a dataset.  I have noticed one thing as I have worked with data scientiests from different backgrounds.  Those who come from a statistics or math background are very concerned with the coefficient estimation while people from an applied science background only concentrate on the overall model quality.  Part of this might be due to how the two groups use the model after fitting - the more theoretical science backgrounds are interested in calculating probabilities and odds from the model and the applied science backgrounds are interested in reproduceability and forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some important skills when performing linear regression that I learned from the theoretical scientists:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incorporating data types into models
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Continuous&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Binary&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Categorical&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Non-linear&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluate Model with Residuals
    * Normality Assumption Check - Plot Y estimated versus Y known
    * Independence of Residuals - Plot Residuals versus Y estimated
    * Verify Constant Variance (Homeoskedascity) - Plot Residuals versus Y estimated
    * Check for Multicolinearity - Calculate VIF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feature Diagnotics
    * Forward Selection
    * Backward Selection
    * Stepwise Regression
    * Use Subject Matter Expert (SME) Input to find important factors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once each feature shows significance, perform additional analysis
    * Calculate Probabilities
    * Calculate Odds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my engineering experiences we would also perform a sensitivity assessment.  This could be done by inputing a lot of inputs or by creating extreme case studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="tech" /><category term="Tech" /><category term="ml" /><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html">Regression is not a topic that I originally spent much time thinking about but as I started to get more involved with analyzing large dataset, I found myself learning more about regression so I coud extract the most out of a dataset. I have noticed one thing as I have worked with data scientiests from different backgrounds. Those who come from a statistics or math background are very concerned with the coefficient estimation while people from an applied science background only concentrate on the overall model quality. Part of this might be due to how the two groups use the model after fitting - the more theoretical science backgrounds are interested in calculating probabilities and odds from the model and the applied science backgrounds are interested in reproduceability and forecasting.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/pencils.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/pencils.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SQL…</title><link href="/articles/tech/2023-02-16-sql/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SQL…" /><published>2023-02-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:05:02-06:00</updated><id>/articles/tech/sql</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/tech/2023-02-16-sql/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SQL is a definite requirement for anyone who is interested in doing data work.  Here are some basics from work I have done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic Selects With Where&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subqueries in the Select and Where Clauses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic Selects With Order By and Limit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selects with Aggregations With Group By&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selects with Aggregations with Group By and Having&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Window Functions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Common Table Expression (CTE)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recursive CTE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="tech" /><category term="Tech" /><category term="etl" /><summary type="html">SQL is a definite requirement for anyone who is interested in doing data work. Here are some basics from work I have done:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/search.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/search.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Preprocessing…</title><link href="/articles/tech/2023-02-10-preprocessing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preprocessing…" /><published>2023-02-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:04:43-06:00</updated><id>/articles/tech/preprocessing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/tech/2023-02-10-preprocessing/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preprocessing might be one of the less appreciated steps in data science.  If you believe in the Pareto Principle then about 80% of one’s time is spent doing Feature Selection and Preprocessing is a significant part of those steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imputing Missing Data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encoding Categorical Variables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transforming Numerical Variables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performing Variable Discretization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eleminating Outliers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extracting Date and Time Features&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating Features from Time Series&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performing Feature Scaling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating New Features&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extracting Features from Relational Data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="tech" /><category term="Tech" /><category term="preprocessing" /><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">Preprocessing might be one of the less appreciated steps in data science. If you believe in the Pareto Principle then about 80% of one’s time is spent doing Feature Selection and Preprocessing is a significant part of those steps.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/steps.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/steps.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Personal Growth…</title><link href="/articles/person/personal/2023-01-27-personal-growth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personal Growth…" /><published>2023-01-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:02:45-06:00</updated><id>/articles/person/personal/personal-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/person/personal/2023-01-27-personal-growth/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last article was a bit long so hopefully this one is more concise.  Although this article is an important topic - it’s about personal growth.  Everything from this past year where I think I have expanded my current skills or identified a potential preference that brings joy to myself.  Below is a short list of some of my key findings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Long term interest:  Detailed Analytics&lt;/code&gt;:   Recently, I had an opportunity to work on a project where the type of work varied drastically.  Sometimes I would be doing analytics, somtimes I would be doing collaborative work, and other times I might monitoring a system looking for failures that needed escalated.  What I realized is that I find great comfort doing detailed analytics work.  It became obvious that I do not get tired or bored doing this work.  I was also very proud of my accomplishments and found it easy to push to get the most value out of each project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Distancing myself from busy-body work&lt;/code&gt;:  I have always been able to adapt to almost any situation and have learned to tolerate aspects of the situation that I find frustrating, but in 2022 I realized that I have always hated being bombarded with requests.  Now, this might sound like a normal expections of a job but I am referring to a role where a new request comes in every few minutes that needs attention - sort of the customer service type role but can also be found in technical roles.  I had a role where I would get an email, slack message, and app alert from each source every couple minutes and I needed to immediately respond and on top of that I needed to monitor several dashboards on a very frequent basis.  I could do it all but this would be constant for hours and realized that my introverted self just became exhausted with this work.  This type of work in limited bursts is fine but not 40% of my work hours for a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OOP and Simulations&lt;/code&gt;:  I really enjoyed some of my coding projects this past year.  My favorite and often most challenging study was expanding my experience with making object oriented programs which often centered around building simulations.  I motivation was a YouTube video about Decision Science - similar to data science but with more emphasis on evaluating what is the value of ideas to the organization.  After looking at the open source tools for simulation, I realized that there was an incredible amount of potential to explore dynamic problems that often machine learning can not capture very effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SQL Projects&lt;/code&gt;:  I was finally able to write Advanced SQL off my todo list.  I knew fundamental concepts but never had to do a full ETL project.  In total I did about three projects that started with messy data and went through all the steps to get it into a cloud or local database.  Afterwards, I kept adding new data to it and checking to see if the database function well and was easy to access the information.  After a handful of projects, I think the only topic still on my SQL todo list is to do a project where I use recursive CTE.  I have learned about them but never really needed to incorporate them into a project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;I'm decent with Tableau&lt;/code&gt;:  I always thought I was not very good with Tableau but it turns out that I have very similar capabilities as those who use Tableau on a regular basis.  It was a bit shocking because I have always discounted this skill.  I also taught a 1.5 hour class on the subject this year when an instructor was unable to make it to the class.  I did pretty good I think for only discussing everything from memory and only 30 minutes advance notice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;I'm typically a good listener&lt;/code&gt;:  This is a trait that I realized that &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; many people have within the data science field.  Too many times this past year, I witnessed people answering questions that were never asked or going on tangents.  I think this is why I find mentoring others be very natural.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Project Management&lt;/code&gt;: It seems as if project management is my de facto role.  When in a group I seem to be the one that plans out the steps and wants to do a work breakdown structure.  Breaking down projects in small components and managing their execution seems like the obvious first step.  What do other people do?  My experience is that confusion is the alternative but maybe there are ways - I guess it works for Jazz musicians.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="person" /><category term="Personal" /><category term="professionalism" /><summary type="html">My last article was a bit long so hopefully this one is more concise. Although this article is an important topic - it’s about personal growth. Everything from this past year where I think I have expanded my current skills or identified a potential preference that brings joy to myself. Below is a short list of some of my key findings:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/growth.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/growth.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2022 Interviews…</title><link href="/articles/person/personal/2022-11-25-interviews/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022 Interviews…" /><published>2022-11-25T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:02:18-06:00</updated><id>/articles/person/personal/interviews</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/person/personal/2022-11-25-interviews/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By September 2022, I had begun distributing my resume to potential employers.  It was somewhat of an odd experience - partially because I had not truly done an interview since 2018 and partially because everything is now performed online.  I had sent out resumes in February 2020, as I was finishing my data science certificate program at Northwestern, but everything was shutting down due to COVID by the next month and all hiring just stopped.  I think I had applied for 20 positions at that time.  This time I applied for only 8 positions but each one was something that I thought would be a very good fit and happily had 4 positive responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial interviews were very similar to my past interviews.  Most of them were with human resources personnel over the phone and was just a general discussion about my interests and background.  I find these discussions to be very beneficial since I have a chance to ask about the ambiguous aspects of the job posting; although, many times I am told that only the hiring manager can provide details.  In general, I was able to get a sense of what the job is like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the four initial phone interviews, I went on to do two second round interviews and I rejected one offer for a second interview and I was not selected for another second round interview.  Luckily, my two favorite options were interested in me.  The interview that I turned down was due to concerns that the job would have a very limited use of modern tools and that the actual job did not match the job posting.  The second interview and third interviews were with the hiring manager and then with multiple coworkers.  After all the interviews, it took around 6 weeks to get a response since I was the first candidate interviewed for both positions.  Both companies made offers at about the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What differed from my past experiences was that neither company offered for me to visit the office and talk to the team about what they do and how they do it.  This was discussed during the second and third interviews but in a very time constrained manner.  I asked additional questions about what to expect after I was told I would get an offer and I did get reasonable answers but much of it was deferred to later because I was told that I would receive two to six months of training before being completely onboarded.  Everyone seemed very likeable and positive about their roles and the hybrid work schedule was said to be working well.  I have had concerns about onboarding with most people working from home - it seems like this would cause problems in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of receiving an offer was very brief compared to past experiences and was completely negotiated by the recruiter and not the hiring manager.  Shortly after my followup questions, I received a verbal offer from the recruiter and was immediatly asked to discuss salary.  This was actually an unplanned phone call and the recruiter was a bit abrupt when outlining the salary and benefits.  I asked for a small bump in salary because I knew the basics of the other offer I would be getting but I had not received anything in writing yet.  The recruiter contacted me the next day with a final offer and gave me roughly five days to make a decision.  I thought this was a bit fast considering I had waited six weeks for their interview process to finish. After a couple days, I accepted the offer and received a confirmation from the recruiter but that was actually the last I ever heard from that person.  This was a bit odd because they entered a start date that I had not agreed upon and all documentation from that point forward was from an automated system.  In total, I think the entire process occurred during one work week - from followup questions to offer to acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in summary, the process was much less personal than my past experiences.  Everything was done online and often details were omitted.  Upon follow messages, some clarity was provided but it required asking very detailed questions to get the necessary information.  The one change I would make now is to push for more clarity regarding their onboarding process.  In the end, I really liked the company as a whole but the onboarding process and the long-term details for my particular role were not explained well.  Within my first few weeks, I realized what seemed like very manageable tasks I had done routinely in the past were part of a time consuming, poorly designed workflow and the training was not very good either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first and only time in my career, I was not able to speed through onboarding and didn’t really see how I would thrive in this environment - it seemed like I would spend all my time asking questions about what I would consider standard operating procedures and the responses often resulted in vague and misleading answers.  After multiple discussions with my coworkers and verifying that everything was going according to plan with my manager, I began to weigh the benefits of continuing at that role.  I realized that even after I learned the core information for the position, I would still be working within a frustrating workflow.  So after only six weeks on the job, I resigned.  I’m probably lucky that the initial training did not go well - by the fourth week, I was designing my own work breakdown structure (WBS) which helped me understand what I should expect after several months on the job and it was a bit disheartening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Check out my next article which will be about what I learned about myself from this experience.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="person" /><category term="Personal" /><category term="professionalism" /><summary type="html">By September 2022, I had begun distributing my resume to potential employers. It was somewhat of an odd experience - partially because I had not truly done an interview since 2018 and partially because everything is now performed online. I had sent out resumes in February 2020, as I was finishing my data science certificate program at Northwestern, but everything was shutting down due to COVID by the next month and all hiring just stopped. I think I had applied for 20 positions at that time. This time I applied for only 8 positions but each one was something that I thought would be a very good fit and happily had 4 positive responses.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/interview.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/interview.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Work Schedules…</title><link href="/articles/person/personal/2022-06-04-work-schedule/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Schedules…" /><published>2022-06-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T16:01:44-06:00</updated><id>/articles/person/personal/work-schedule</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/person/personal/2022-06-04-work-schedule/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must say that I have benefitted from the work from home experiences of the past few years.  By saving two hours each day on commuting and being able to utilize my time at home very effectively, I have been able to add significant time developing data skills.  With my schedule from before the pandemic, I don’t know if I could have had enough time or energy to be able to include meaningful learning.  So I give strong praise for work at home for its ability to support independent research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side prior to the pandemic, I would often go to meetup.com meetings hosted in downtown Chicago about python, machine learning, and database applications.  These seminars were grade and they continue online but the part that could not be duplicated is the wisdom sharing and battle stories tha were shared among the guests at the in-person meetings.  I learned so much from hearing about the experiences people had and it gave me a lot of perspective about what this career included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really synpathsize with employers now.  On one hand people can become better employees through easier access to technical training.  On the other hand, the interpersonal discussions provided a context that helped me plan my future career.  I could see everyone going back to full time in the office; although not ideal, but I definitely don’t think work from home all the time is good for professional development and collaborative work.  I tend to think that working several days from the office and but also having several days where one can work from home to be very nice compromise.&lt;br /&gt;
home versus office&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><category term="person" /><category term="Personal" /><category term="professionalism" /><summary type="html">I must say that I have benefitted from the work from home experiences of the past few years. By saving two hours each day on commuting and being able to utilize my time at home very effectively, I have been able to add significant time developing data skills. With my schedule from before the pandemic, I don’t know if I could have had enough time or energy to be able to include meaningful learning. So I give strong praise for work at home for its ability to support independent research.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/remote_work.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/remote_work.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>