<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2022-07-13T11:44:03-05:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ERIN WILLS</title><subtitle>By possessing both technical and managerial skills,  Erin is highly adaptive particularly with learning and teaching new technology.
</subtitle><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Work Schedules…</title><link href="/articles/2022-06-04-work-schedule/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Schedules…" /><published>2022-06-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T00:06:25-05:00</updated><id>/articles/work-schedule</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-06-04-work-schedule/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must say that I have benefitted from the work from home experiences of the past few years.  By saving two hours each day on commuting and being able to utilize my time at home very effectively, I have been able to add significant time developing data skills.  With my schedule from before the pandemic, I don’t know if I could have had enough time or energy to be able to include meaningful learning.  So I give strong prise for work at home for its ability to support independent research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side prior to the pandemic, I would often go to meetup.com meetings hosted in downtown Chicago about python, machine learning, and database applications.  These seminars were grade and they continue online but the part that could not be duplicated is the wisdom sharing and battle stories tha were shared among the guests at the in-person meetings.  I learned so much from hearing about the experiences people had and it gave me a lot of perspective about what this career included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really synpathsize with employers now.  On one hand people can become better employees through easier access to technical training.  On the other hand, the interpersonal discussions provided a context that helped me plan my future career.  I could see everyone going back to full time in the office; although not ideal, but I definitely don’t think work from home all the time is good for professional development and collaborative work.  I tend to think that working several days from the office and but also having several days where one can work from home to be very nice compromise.&lt;br /&gt;
home versus office&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">I must say that I have benefitted from the work from home experiences of the past few years. By saving two hours each day on commuting and being able to utilize my time at home very effectively, I have been able to add significant time developing data skills. With my schedule from before the pandemic, I don’t know if I could have had enough time or energy to be able to include meaningful learning. So I give strong prise for work at home for its ability to support independent research.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/remote_work.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/remote_work.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Early 2022</title><link href="/articles/2022-06-03-current2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early 2022" /><published>2022-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T03:59:22-05:00</updated><id>/articles/current2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-06-03-current2022/">&lt;p&gt;I made some changes in early 2022 after realizing in 2021 that my schedule was just not productive with my future interests.  By mid-2021, I had completed my data science certificate program at Northwestern University, two rotations as a teaching assistant with the same program, 4 data science online classes, and multiple self-study projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between my full time job at Northwestern and my professional development, my schedule was typically booked between 6am to 10pm everyday except for Sunday.  A slow weeks was 90 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A challenge to this schedule was that I switched between technologies multiple times each day.  My job at Northwestern was not a technical position but I did whatever was needed.  Aince I could code, there were many tasks that had been done manually but in cases where a quick turnaround was needed then I would often automate the task.  Switching technologies and being busy with the certificate program always made me feel that I was not advancing my skills - as soon as I would be getting into the zone with one technology it was time for me to move to the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 2022, I started to work remotely doing several technology projects on a gig-like situation.  It was kind of a odd situation but it worked well for both of us since we both needed some flexibility in our schedules.  I wanted to continue teaching at the certificate program and my Northwestern schedule was not going to accomodate my schedule well and I was scheduled for some foot surgery where I would be off my feet for weeks and have some physical therapy afterwards.  I also wanted to see family for a few weeks - my parents are older and had only been able to see them once during the two years of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a great experience so far.  My schedule is still busy but I have been able to go more indepth with technologies and I feel that my fluency when coding in python, sql, javascript and other languages has gotten much better.  I have also become a better teaching assistant because I went back to the lessons and modified them and polished up some of my terminology and explanations.  I definitely had a feeling of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;imposter syndrome&lt;/code&gt; prior to my changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at my six month checkpoint, I feel that I am ready to explore more areas of the data science field.  The skills of the trade are well within my grasp and now I am working more on the art form of the trade.  My current personal goals are to expand my experiences with simulations, machine learning algorithms, time series analysis, and geospacial analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I should have probabably made this jump about two years ago.  Working that schedule did not really let me focus and process the meaning of what I was learning.  The one truly wise decision I made was working as a data science teaching assistant.  The experience of reading different styles of coding and explaining concepts in different ways has helped develop a strong foundation.  Now I just need some real world case studies to apply these tools to make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">I made some changes in early 2022 after realizing in 2021 that my schedule was just not productive with my future interests. By mid-2021, I had completed my data science certificate program at Northwestern University, two rotations as a teaching assistant with the same program, 4 data science online classes, and multiple self-study projects.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/lets_change.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/lets_change.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Before 2022…</title><link href="/articles/2022-06-03-earlier2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Before 2022…" /><published>2022-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T03:57:20-05:00</updated><id>/articles/earlier2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-06-03-earlier2022/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would say that I have been developing my data science knowledge-base since the summer of 2019.  Around that time, I took several Standford University online classes and started a six month Northwestern University Data Science Certificate Program and since Spring 2020 I have been a data science teaching assistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I carefully decided to commit my time and effort of this transition after attending nearly weekly meetup.com meetings for a year.  After talking to members of the Python and PostgreSQL meetups and attending some industry based seminars from MATTER, I decided this was a career move I would really like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s odd to say this but a benefit of the pandemic was the opening up of my schedule so that my days were no longer 10 to 12 hours at my primary employer.  I often had 2 hours of commuting time and multiple hours of random meetings that I would get pulled into.  Due to the pandemic, I could add 3-4 hours daily for professional development.  I have more information about this in my post “Work Schedules” but over the past two years I have been able to fit into my schedule over 30 hours per week related to data science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I announced in June 2021 that I would leave my Northwestern job in December 2021.  In 2021, I was actually working more hours dedicated to my role at the data science bootcamp and professional development than I was doing at Northwestern University.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">So I would say that I have been developing my data science knowledge-base since the summer of 2019. Around that time, I took several Standford University online classes and started a six month Northwestern University Data Science Certificate Program and since Spring 2020 I have been a data science teaching assistant.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/busy.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/busy.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Professional Philosophy</title><link href="/articles/2022-06-02-philosophy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Professional Philosophy" /><published>2022-06-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T04:00:41-05:00</updated><id>/articles/philosophy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-06-02-philosophy/">&lt;p&gt;As an engineer or in any role that I have had, I always looked at my job as doing two different tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase Yield (Product Output)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increrase Efficiency (Decrease Cost)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;OR the combination of the two for a blockbuster project.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took great comfort in this philosophy when working on projects and some mild anxiousness if I was working on projects that had low value.  Let’s be honest about it - you can calculate what the value of an employee is and whether they are making or losing money for a company (that is more or less true; there are some caveats to this idea).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This perspective is often what drives my thoughts when I consider data projects.  What value is in the analysis?  If it has low potential value then why work on it unless that work can be used else where later for high value projects.  I guess I would say that I work on projects not because I want to try new things but because I want to generate value.  I could go on about this subject but I will hold off.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">As an engineer or in any role that I have had, I always looked at my job as doing two different tasks: Increase Yield (Product Output) Increrase Efficiency (Decrease Cost) OR the combination of the two for a blockbuster project.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/trend.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/trend.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Design Principles</title><link href="/articles/2022-06-02-design/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design Principles" /><published>2022-06-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-12T03:55:17-05:00</updated><id>/articles/design</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-06-02-design/">&lt;p&gt;I add this equation to my frontpage because it was used at a seminar during my junior year in college by a guest lecturer who was originally from DOW Chemical.  There was nothing complicated about the seminar but the concept presented was incredibly insightful and concise.  The topic was about Design Principles and here are a couple heuristics that I remember vividly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good designs avoid needless complexity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good designers do the least amount of work possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AND the quality of a solution is proportional to the number of scenarios it solves out all the potential problems that exist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was this last bullet point, where we consider all the potential combinations, that gave me additional focus - keep it simple, do what is needed and move to the next project, and develop your engineering intuition such that you can foresee problems before they occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(\LARGE_{n} C_r=\frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}\)  &lt;br /&gt;
Combination
&lt;!-- {:.figcaption} --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">I add this equation to my frontpage because it was used at a seminar during my junior year in college by a guest lecturer who was originally from DOW Chemical. There was nothing complicated about the seminar but the concept presented was incredibly insightful and concise. The topic was about Design Principles and here are a couple heuristics that I remember vividly: Good designs avoid needless complexity Good designers do the least amount of work possible AND the quality of a solution is proportional to the number of scenarios it solves out all the potential problems that exist.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/planning.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/planning.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ideal Profession…</title><link href="/articles/2022-06-01-ideal-profession/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ideal Profession…" /><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T04:04:48-05:00</updated><id>/articles/ideal-profession</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-06-01-ideal-profession/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well this is a difficult question.  I think if I really knew I would have been doing that job years ago.  For me, I originally went into chemical engineering because I enjoyed the types of problems I was presented and over time I used more and more technology.  It’s quite amazing to me when I think about how I went from a rural area with little internet and computer needs to programming Distributed Control Systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I wanted to do something a bit different than working in chemical facilities.  I did have strong opinions about how people are trained in technical areas and thought I could go into education technology to improve post-secondary and professional development experiences.  I realized pretty quickly that there are not many applications of technology really being used in education that improves the experience and most education providers don’t invest much money in development of new revolutionary tools.  If I wanted to do that then it is better to just develop technology in my free time and eventually create a company because its a tough industry and most companies want to generate revenue with the least amount of risk.  I continue to think about this topic.  It was probably my driving reason for working for a education technology company and their bootcamps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where am I now on this subject?  I’m pretty open to most industries.  I can not say I have a specific field that is ideal.  I probably lean toward geospacial analysis because it is just a topic that seems to provide so many interesting answers and generates interesting questions - it’s almost like its a subject that is never brought up by anyone.  I also seem to enjoy data extraction and cleaning much more than most people.  It makes me feel a bit odd - it’s also a subject that many don’t like but I find it natural to explore data and try to find that bit that has been overlooked and then see what changes when models are run on that data.  I think this must be a habit from working with chemical process data that was so messy that when you finally found that trend that explained why things work the way they do and you can generate extra margin from it - that was a great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">Well this is a difficult question. I think if I really knew I would have been doing that job years ago. For me, I originally went into chemical engineering because I enjoyed the types of problems I was presented and over time I used more and more technology. It’s quite amazing to me when I think about how I went from a rural area with little internet and computer needs to programming Distributed Control Systems.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/collaboration.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/collaboration.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Inspirations</title><link href="/articles/2022-06-01-inspirations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inspirations" /><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T04:03:16-05:00</updated><id>/articles/inspirations</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-06-01-inspirations/">&lt;p&gt;What I am about to write should be Part II of my Philosophy post because it had a pretty profound affect on how I thought about my career.&lt;br /&gt;
If my memory serves me, all this occurred in one week near the beginning of my senior year at Purdue University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a lecture about engineering design, the instructor talked about a conference seminar from the past year where the speaker proposed that design could be described by one equation.  Essentially, what he wrote up on the dry erease board was the probability density function from  negative infinity to positive infinity.  He asked the class to explain the equation and after a couple feeble attempts and one comical attempt he continued to explain my paraphrased version of it:&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;A designer, whether engineer or other trade, considers all the potential negative outcomes related to a problem they are trying to solve.  All outcomes are expressed in this equation and the quality of your design is based on how many and which outcomes your design can accomodate.  The more circumstances, as in the greater percent of the area under the curve, that can be addressed then the better the design but it is highly unlikely you will solve all the issues as almost all designs come with tradeoffs.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was just truly impressed with this seminar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other event that week was a seminar with former Dow Chemical CEO, Paul Oreffice.  Now, his history as CEO is a bit controversial due to the companies practices in the 1970’s related to chemicals sold to the US Army and other practices but he had an incredible story about his early career.  It was a long story but the gist of it was something like:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Be smart with how you view risk.  It is something you will have to become astute with managing but if it truly doesn't have significant reprecussions as in harm or moral conflicts then there is not much preventing you for going for it.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This was after he told some stories about risks he took that could have gone either way but in the end worked out for him or had negligible impact but provided him great experience for tasks he later faced.  With that all being said, this also prompted several questions about ethical business practices which he provided a answer to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have an honorable mention memory from that week.  My controls class began each lecture from the first week to the last week with listing the 5 most important parts to an engineer’s job.  Number one was the only emphasized selection every time and the topic was &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Safety&lt;/code&gt;.  The lecture I remember the most was about the tragedy that occured at the Union Carbide plant in Bhopal, India in 1984.  A preventible accident occurred where a toxic gas cloud was released and passed over a highly populated, incredibly poor area just outside the facility gates.  Thousands of people died immediately and many more over the weeks afterwards.  I remembered this discussion because I had worked with an engineer who worked at Union Carbide and he had talked about how this ethical issue had such an incredible effect on the company because US employees were so upset and ashamed something like this could happen that employees began quitting the company.  The company lost so much talent that employees knew it was a sinking ship.  The dynamics of this situation are interesting and the role of leadership and the lack of it in this scenario are worht studying.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">What I am about to write should be Part II of my Philosophy post because it had a pretty profound affect on how I thought about my career. If my memory serves me, all this occurred in one week near the beginning of my senior year at Purdue University.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/seminar.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/seminar.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A brief history…</title><link href="/articles/2022-05-29-bio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A brief history…" /><published>2022-05-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T04:06:16-05:00</updated><id>/articles/bio</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-05-29-bio/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I can say I have had a very broad range of experiences thus far in my career but the common theme is that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;I have always done a little bit of everything at the places I have worked&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
This is not exactly what I had envisioned when coming out of college - I thought I would become a specialist but due to the nature of what was needed, I shifted roles every couple months and adapted to new technologies so by default I think that makes me a generalist.  I’m beginning to doubt that thought after meeting multiple data scientiests and am starting to think I would fit well in a data career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some reasons I think I would fit well in this field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Science incorporates a broad range of technologies that are always changing.  My background largely supports the foundations.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Engineering background with stats, math, and computer science technical skills.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Strong understanding of Web Development Technologies which make database, visualization, and webscraping tasks much easier.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Comfortable working with large amounts of data including messy data in multiple formats and technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consistently learning new technologies.  Let’s be honest, much of the work is selecting the right technology for the specific neeed.  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;article&lt;/code&gt; about how technolgies can be interchangeable - pandas, sql, js, etc.  its about moving data around&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have now been a Data Science teaching assistant for about 2 years and have worked with multiple instructors.  I feel that I am pretty competent in many of the areas and what I don’t know, I can figure out quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working well with others is critical to satisfying a clients needs and effectively executing a complex project.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Truly enjoy developing projects from conceptualization to execution and process improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Strong communication, project management and collaboration skills&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’m honest, straight-forward, non-adversarial, optimistic, and can indulge people when needed and ignore people when necessary.  So for those difficult to work with people, I greatly disappoint them by not stoking any fires.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The melding of technologies is necessary to truly accomplish most tasks. Individual skills are great but interrelationship among them is where money can be made.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Okay, so this is an area where I think I can really excel. Python (SQLAlchemy, Flask, Pandas, graphing libraries, ML Libraries, etc), SQL, Databases, R, Web Technologies, Tableau, etc.  These are tools that can be used together to do some pretty useful and automated tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I am looking to become more profiecient in Discrete Event Simulations and incorporating my data skills.  I enjoy combining theoretical calculations, modeling process data, and considering hypothetical situations.  It’s truly going back to my favorite engineering experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I think I could sucessfully move between analyst, visualization, machine learning, and data organization tasks quite readily.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;My greatest challenge right now is to stay up-to-date with new technology and practical skills.  Working with at a company with a good technology stack and data culture would elevate my compencies.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Do it all for you systems” are a great concept but one solution rarely works for most situations so adapting technology should be expected.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I worked on a project where the client really wanted to use Microsoft Sharepoint and some of their work could be implemented on that system but parts of it could have been done much better and faster with other tools.  I setup the tools and got the other tasks to work and I only hope someone maintained it after I left.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">I think I can say I have had a very broad range of experiences thus far in my career but the common theme is that I have always done a little bit of everything at the places I have worked. This is not exactly what I had envisioned when coming out of college - I thought I would become a specialist but due to the nature of what was needed, I shifted roles every couple months and adapted to new technologies so by default I think that makes me a generalist. I’m beginning to doubt that thought after meeting multiple data scientiests and am starting to think I would fit well in a data career.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/notes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/notes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sweet Home Chicago</title><link href="/articles/2022-05-01-chicago/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sweet Home Chicago" /><published>2022-05-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-13T02:18:10-05:00</updated><id>/articles/chicago</id><content type="html" xml:base="/articles/2022-05-01-chicago/">&lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;I LOVE CHICAGO.  Just plain and simple - its a city and neighborhoods with traditions that make me feel proud and energized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have lived in many different areas - Indiana, Louisiana, Alabama, Tennessee, Illinois, etc - but despite how hard I work, I am always able to find something to do in Chicago that refreshes me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past two years, I have largely worked 7:30am to 5:00pm at my full time job and then 14 hours each week working as a teaching assistant at Northwestern’s Data Science Certificate Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the long hours, the late evening restaurant order or walk along the Riverwalk with friends makes it very satisfying.  With summer approaching and fewer COVID restrictions, I look forward to going to festivals and events and spending more time outside.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Erin Wills</name><email>ejw.data@gmail.com</email></author><category term="articles" /><summary type="html">I LOVE CHICAGO. Just plain and simple - its a city and neighborhoods with traditions that make me feel proud and energized. I have lived in many different areas - Indiana, Louisiana, Alabama, Tennessee, Illinois, etc - but despite how hard I work, I am always able to find something to do in Chicago that refreshes me.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/sawyer-bengtson-tnv84LOjes4-unsplash_resized.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/sawyer-bengtson-tnv84LOjes4-unsplash_resized.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>